RAFAEL A. MIRANDA AGUILAR

7630 Sunfield Circle Apt 102 • Raleigh, North Carolina, 27617 • 919-610-2609 rafa8626@gmail.com

SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

A self-motivated senior software engineer with 10 years of web development experience. Expert level proficiency in LAMP technologies. An enthusiastic researcher of new solutions based on Web 2.0 technologies with broad database knowledge. Background includes work with PHP, CSS(3), Javascript (specially, jQuery), XML, JSON and MySQL. Bilingual, ability to speak, read and write in both English and Spanish. Currently learning Italian. Fosters an entrepreneurial spirit and strives to inspire customers and co-workers.

TECHNICAL SUMMARY

Languages: PHP, Javascript (ES5, ES6), HTML(5), XML, JSON, CSS(3)

Platforms: Linux, Mac OSX, AWS DBMS: MySQL, MongoDB (beginner)

Frameworks/CMS/CMF: Drupal 6, jQuery, Twitter Bootstrap, Zend Framework (1 & 2), AngularJS, Ionic

Version Control: GIT

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Tech Lead -- MedSims from Medscape/WebMD. Durham, NC present

2015 -

- Lead SCRUM meetings, assisted creation of backlog and organizing tasks for Dev Team to achieve 3 concurrent
 projects by using Agile approach, which led us to deliver those products in a matter of 6 months, leading to major
 improvements for the end users of the Authoring Tool, as well as the kernel and data reports delivered to the clients.
- Co-developed new DB and code infrastructure 7 months that allowed the preparation for the rewriting of entire simulation platform, as well as the creation of new Authoring Tool to manipulate cases and simulation behaviors.
- Migrated old product from Zend Framework 1 to Zend Framework 2, including DB migration and code refactoring in terms of Javascript and PHP to reduce amount of code and improve readability as well as performance, in a matter of 12 months, using jQuery, Bootstrap and Zend Framework 2, which allowed a new product to fit across browsers and devices, and also to be expanded in more new applications.
- Co-developed new Authoring Tool in a matter of 6 months using Zend Framework 2 and jQuery, to reduce time of
 cases creation in a 70%, increasing Content Team productivity in 50%, and opening the doors to create/customize
 simulations easily and quickly.

Senior Software Engineer -- TheraSim, Inc. Durham, NC

2011 - 2014

- Maintained certain simulation system areas into the GUI simulator by fixing issues and adding new features using Zend Framework, jQuery, OO Javascript, CSS3 and HTML5, which improved the speed of the project in a 40%.
- Translated in Spanish GUI to allow the company to expand its market in Spain and other latin countries during 2012.
- Created responsive-cross-browser GUI and backend for demo for Johnson and Johnson in a matter of 2 months, using Twitter Bootstrap, jQuery and Zend Framework 2 as well as using best practices related to performance improvements, setting the basis for a template that would allow the company to extend its products to other devices, such as iPad, iPod and smartphones.
- Created a custom CSS framework integrating full size video, interactive screens and other features for a prototype for Georgia Health University using MediaElementJS, jQuery UI, jQuery, CSS3, HTML5 and OO PHP in 2 weeks.
- Developed code for Chameleon platform to be used as a new simulator for above project.
- Worked as a UX, Front-end and Back-end Developer in project in MedSims 3.0
 (https://demos3.medsims.com/mel-demo), creating a cross-browser/cross-device/immersive web app using Zend Framework 2, Google Analytics, Twitter Bootstrap 3, as well as many best practices for web app development. Application targets IE8+, Firefox, Chrome, Safari, as well as iOS and Android devices.
- Created terminal-oriented PHP script and improved process to update company's drug dictionary in a matter of 2 weeks, reducing the time of this process from 8 hours to less than 15 minutes.

Web Developer -- Justia Inc. Coahuila, Mexico

2009 - 2011

- Developed and co-maintained 27 crawler scripts using object-oriented PHP and MySQL that generate daily content for 3 different websites (http://auto-recalls.justia.com, http://aw.justia.com/cases), oriented to position the business into the top Google's search results for free legal information consulting.
- Created an internal tool by integrating Copyscape API and cron jobs, using object-oriented PHP and MySQL, which
 allowed other teams to speed their duplicated content research tasks by 70%.
- Co-developed a complex Q&A website (http://answers.justia.com), as well as several administrative pages for it, in

- 15 months; also, co-developed a document storage website pilot in 5 months. Both of them using Drupal 6.0, MySQL, JSON, XML, Google Maps API and jQuery.
- Created demo for an iGoogle-like dashboard in 2 weeks using Drupal 6.0 and CSS, based on personal research conducted about DOM manipulation and AJAX callbacks (with jQuery), after recognizing a need and acting on own initiative.
- Maintained 3 Drupal custom modules and created a new one for http://www.jurispro.com to add new features and fix issues that came up in a period of 3 months.
- Gathered web team together and led them through a process whereby we came up with solutions to resolve interpersonal differences; as a result, after 2 months, concerns and complaints about the team decreased by 85%.

Research and Development Manager -- CIIST. Hidalgo, Mexico

2008 - 2009

- Developed an administrative panel and website for Madame Chantal in 2 months to improve business' identity and expand its Internet demography using PHP, MySQL and AJAX (XAJAX Framework).
- Created small CRM for Exportaciones Textiles Mexicana providing the organization an entry into 3 critical areas: sales, storage and maintenance, after only 4 months, using PHP, MySQL and AJAX (XAJAX Framework).

Open Source Contributor -- GitHub Community

- 2015-2017: Major contributor on MediaElementJS: upgraded from 2.x to 4.x version, improved UI and integrated different media types in the player (native HLS, M(PEG)-DASH, native FLV, Vimeo, Twitch, etc.), migrated from ES5 to ES6, turning code base into framework-agnositc, added unit tests with Mocha, Chai and Istanbul (https://github.com/mediaelement/mediaelement/commits?author=rafa8626)
- 2015-2017: Major contributor on <u>MediaElementJS Plugins</u>: added 5 new plugins (Chromecast, Airplay, Preview, Playlist and Quality Chooser) and improved/maintained 11 other plugins
 (https://github.com/mediaelement/mediaelement-plugins/commits?author=rafa8626)
- 2017: Integrated HTML5 video events and missing methods for <u>Google VRView</u> project (https://github.com/googlevr/vrview/pull/177, https://github.com/googlevr/vrview/pull/212 and https://github.com/googlevr/vrview/pull/128)
- 2017: Assisted <u>WordPress</u> to upgrade MediaElement into core project (https://github.com/xwp/wordpress-develop/pull/232 and https://github.com/xwp/wordpress-develop/pull/232 and https://github.com/xwp/wordpress-develop/pull/232 and https://github.com/xwp/wordpress-develop/pull/232 and https://github.com/xwp/wordpress-develop/pull/232
- 2013: Expanded workflow to allow Vladimir Karlhampidi's <u>Swiper</u> plugin to be more responsive (https://github.com/nolimits4web/Swiper/pull/816)

FREELANCE

- 2015-2017: Modifications to Siberian's MCommerce plugin per client's requests, modifying both PHP and Javascript, including interactions with AngularJS and Ionic (http://app.my-food-app.co.uk/55d47f6c2af0d)
- 2015: Created currency exchange calculator using AngularJS (http://test.dreamsapps.com/calculator/)
- **2015:** Fixed several issues with different behaviors in terms of text manipulation and positioning using vanilla Javascript, jQuery, PHP and FabricJS (http://finansenl.com.pl/magnesy2/)

EDUCATION

BS Computer Sciences – Graduated 2008

Universidad Autónoma del Estado de Hidalgo, Mexico.